U.S. Emergency Board No. 135 Records 5056
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
U.S. Emergency Board No. 135 Records
1945-1961
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
U.S. Emergency Board
5056
2 cubic feet
2 linear ft.
Records (documents).
Transcript of proceedings and exhibits of the Emergency Board No. 135, 1961. Wages and hours case. Pan American World Airways, Inc. and the Flight engineers International Association, PAA Chapter, 1927-1961.
3114908
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Robert J. Smith, January 28, 2013
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 04, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The Emergency Board was established by Executive Order 10919 of February 17, 1961 as a result of the dispute over the terms of a new contract between the Pan American World Airways, Inc. and the Flight Engineers International Associ-ation.
The union submitted proposals for a reduction of flight time hours, increased pay, and additional furlough pay. These demands, which would have necessitated the employment of additional flight engineers at considerable company expense, came at a time when the composition of the cockpit crew was under fire in the airline industry (crew composition controversy). The controversy was one of representation of the flight engineer by either FEIA of ALPA, brought to a head by the National Mediation Board's decision re: United Airlines in favor of unilateral representation by the ALPA (Air Line Pilots Association). As a result of the aforesaid, a presidential commission was established to Investigate this industry wide controversy.
Emergency Board No. 135 was chaired by G. Allan Dash and had as members Arthur Stark and Edward A. Lynch. The board conducted proceedings from April 2k to June 8, 1961, running concurrently, incidentally, with those of the presidential commission,
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5006: U.S. Emergency Board No. 174 Records 5007: U.S. Emergency Board No. 175 Transcripts and Exhibits 5012: Saul Wallen Papers 5027: U.S. Emergency Board No. 178 Transcripts 5030: U.S. Emergency Board No. 179 Exhibits and Related Material 5036: U.S. Emergency Boards under the Railway Labor Act Reports 5037: U.S. Emergency Board No. 81 Records 5038: U.S. Emergency Board No. 94 Records 5039: U.S. Emergency Board No. 98 Records 5040: U.S. Emergency Board No. 106 Records 5042: U.S. Emergency Board No. 111 Records 5043: U.S. Emergency Board No. 114 Records 5044: U.S. Emergency Board No. 116 Reports and Exhibits 5045: U.S. Emergency Board No. 118 Records 5046: U.S. Emergency Board No. 119 Records 5047: U.S. Emergency Board No. 120 Records 5048: U.S. Emergency Board No. 121 Records 5050: U.S. Emergency Board No. 124 Records 5051: U.S. Emergency Board No. 125 Records 5052: U.S. Emergency Board No. 129 Records 5053: U.S. Emergency Board No. 130 Records 5054: U.S. Emergency Board No. 133 Exhibits 5055: U.S. Emergency Board No. 134 Records 5057: U.S. Emergency Board No. 137 Transcript of Proceedings and Exhibits 5058: U.S. Emergency Board No. 138 Records 5059: U.S. Emergency Board No. 142 Records 5060: U.S. Emergency Board No. 145 Records 5061: U.S. Emergency Board No. 146 Records 5062: U.S. Emergency Board No. 154 Records 5064: U.S. Emergency Board No. 169 Transcript of Proceedings and Exhibits 5075: U.S. Emergency Board under the Taft Hartley Act Records 5579: National Mediation Board Emergency Board 180, Train Crew Consists 5934: Arthur Stark Papers on the President's Emergency Board #219
Airlines -- Employees -- Labor unions -- United States -- Sources; Arbitration, Industrial -- United States -- Sources; United States. Emergency Board No. 135; Flight Engineers' International Association; Pan American World Airways, Inc.
3114908
- Transcripts and Carrier Exhibits (Box 1)
  - Transcripts. 17 Volumes. 2008 pages. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - New York Times article regarding Flight Engineers International Association proposal to Presidential Commission for Settlement of Dispute with Pilots Union, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    May 14, 1961
  - Report of Airline Presidential Commission (Summary) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Report of Airline Presidential Commission (Summary) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Statement by the President following receipt of the reports of the Presidential Commission of the Airlines Controversy and the Northeast Airlines Emergency Board (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Report to the President by the Emergency Board - Northeast Airlines (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Pan American Route Map (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chronology of events (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Estimated impact of flight engineer strike of February 1961 on Pan American's gross revenues and estimated average revenue loss per flight engineer employee (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - History of Collective Bargaining Agreements (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Number of Check Engineers, Engineer Officers and Assistant Engineer Officers by Base Station as of April 15, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Distribute of Pan American's airline employees by craft or class as of December 31, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Analysis of total 1960 Airline Payroll (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Summary of Total Flight Engineer Group (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The number and average age of check engineers, engineer officers and assistant engineer officers by base station as of April 15, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Analysis of flight engineer education upon initial employment (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Schedule of last jobs and wage rates of Pan American flight engineers prior to employment by Pan American Airways (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Distribution of 1960 gross earnings of flight engineers who were active for entire year (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Years of service for pay purposed by equipment for check engineers, engineer officers and assistant engineer as of April 15, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Comparison of Pan American Airways and Selected Airlines ratio of international revenue ton miles to total revenue ton miles, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Summary of equipment operated by Pan American Airways, American Airlines, Eastern Air Lines, National Airlines, Northwest Airlines, Trans World Airlines, Voyageur Airlines, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    December 31, 1960
  - Aircraft owned and leased by Pan American Airways, 1946-1960 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Pan American Jet Aircraft on order, delivered and estimated delivery dates of undelivered aircraft, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    April 1, 1961
  - Comparison of definition of "Engineer Officer" provisions of Pan American Airways-Flight Engineers International Association Agreement of October 25, 1957, 1957- 1960 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Also includes Pan American Airways proposal of May 5, 1960 and the Applicable Civil Air Regulations
  - Comparison of missing, internment, prisoner of war or hostage provisions of Pan American Airways-Flight Engineers International Association dated October 25, 1957, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Includes Pan American Airways proposal dated May 5, 1960 and similar provisions of other airline agreements governing non-pilot flight engineers
  - Comparison of Emergency Furlough Provisions of Pan American Airways-Flight Engineers International Association Agreement dated October 25, 1957, 1957- 1960 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Also includes Pan American Airways proposal dated May 5, 1960 and similar provisions of other airline agreements governing non-pilot flight engineers
  - Comparison of Emergency Furlough Provisions of Pan American Airways-Flight Engineers International Association Agreement dated October 25, 1957, 1957- 1960 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Also includes Pan American Airways Proposal dated May 5, 1960 and similar provisions of other Pan American Airways agreements governing emergency furlough
  - Comparison of training and qualifications provisions of Pan American Airways-Flight Engineers International Association Agreement dated October 25, 1957, 1957- 1960 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Also includes Flight Engineers International Association Proposals dated April 15, 1960 and similar provisions of other airline agreements governing non-pilot flight engineers
  - Comparison of seniority list provisions of Pan American Airways-Flight Engineers International Association agreement dated October 25, 1956, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Also includes Flight Engineers International Association proposal dated April 15, 1960 and similar provisions of Pan American Airways agreements governing non-pilot flight engineers
  - Comparison of seniority list provisions of Pan American Airways-Flight Engineers International Association agreement dated October 25, 1957, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Also includes Flight Engineers International Association proposal dated April 15, 1960 and similar provisions of other airline agreements governing non-pilot flight engineers
  - Comparison of furlough pay provisions of Pan American Airways-Flight Engineers International Association agreement dated October 25, 1957, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Comparison of provisions of Pan American Airways-Flight Engineers International Association dated October 25, 1957, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Also includes Flight Engineers International Association proposal dated April 15, 1960 regarding details of and expenses in connection with recall and similar provisions of other airline agreements governing non-pilot flight engineers
  - Comparison of flight engineer pay formula factors as of April 1, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Comparison between the current factors of Pan American Airways and other airlines and factors proposed by Flight Engineers International Association.
  - Comparison of present and proposed engineer officer and assistant engineer officer guarantee (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Comparison of Pan American Airways current engineer officer and assistant engineer officer pay and pay proposed by Flight Engineers International Association (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Comparison of pay for 70, 75, 80, and 85 hours for all equipment
  - Comparison of Pan American flight engineers monthly guarantee hours with the monthly guarantee hours of other carriers employing non-pilot flight engineers (Box 1, Folder 36)
    35A. Comparison of Pan American Airways flight engineer monthly guarantees with non-pilot flight engineer monthly guarantees of other carriers by equipment
  - Comparison of Pan American Airways engineer officer pay on piston equipment at 70, 75, 80, and 85 hours (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Compared with pay of flight engineers and other carriers employing non-pilot flight engineers
  - Comparison of Pan American Airways engineer officer pay on jet equipment at 70, 75, 80, and 85 hours (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Compared with engineer officer pay on carriers employing non-pilot flight engineers on same equipment
  - Comparison of Pan American maximum engineer officer pay at 70, 80, and 85 hours (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Compared with maximum engineer officer pay (on various aircraft) for such aircraft on other carriers employing non-pilot engineers, the industry average of such other carriers, and with Flight Engineers International Association Proposal
  - Analysis of flight engineer utilization summary of annual flight engineer and assistant flight engineer pay and productive hours, 1956-1960 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Also includes a comparison of average pay hours with average productive hours
  - Excerpt from the State of the Union Address of the President to the Congress, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    January 7, 1960
  - Excerpt from report to the President of the Excerpt from report to the President of the United States on the labor dispute in the basic steel industry (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Excerpt from report to the President of Emergency Board created January 13, 1951 in regards to American Airlines, Incorporated and the Air Line Pilots Association number 94 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Excerpt from Basic Facts on Productivity Change, Occasional Paper 63, National Bureau of Economic Research, Incorporated (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Statement regarding average gain in productivity as standard for wage increases (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Excerpt from Productivity and Wage Settlements published by the Chamber of Commerce of the United States, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Comparison of Flight Engineer Officers by Status and Equipment Exclusive of Checks and Supervisors, 1957-1961 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    January 1, 1957-April 15, 1961
  - Excerpt from the current contract between General Motors Corporation and United Auto Workers regarding productivity or improvement wage factors (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Comparison of maximum flight engineer officer and assistant flight engineer officer rates (Box 1, Folder 49)
    Comparison of maximum flight engineer officer and assistant flight engineer officer rates inflated for change in consumer price index and for various productivity improvement factors with current 80 hour DC-8 yields
  - Comparison of 80 hour flight engineer officers maximum yield under 1953 agreement (Box 1, Folder 50)
    Comparison of 80 hour flight engineer officers maximum yield under 1953 agreement inflated for consumer price index change and inflated by various productivity improvement factors to 80 hour flight engineer officers maximum yield under present agreement
  - Comparison of maximum flight engineer officer 80 hour yields of various piston aircraft, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    Comparison of maximum flight engineer officer 80 hour yields of various piston aircraft inflated for Consumer Price Index change and for various productivity improvement factors to maximum flight engineer officer 80 hour yields of various higher rated air
  - Average yield from passenger, cargo, and United States mail, 1946-1960 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Analysis of percentages of increase, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    June 1, 1957. Also includes Flight Engineers International Association agreement over previous rates and of percentage differentials between DC-7C rates and jet rates in present agreement at 70, 80, and 85 hours yields for top rate flight engineer officer
  - Analysis of increased annual cost of promoting assistant engineer officers to engineer officers as proposed by Flight Engineers International Association (Box 1, Folder 54)
    Promotion would have occurred upon completion of three and one-half years of service as assistant engineer officers as proposed
  - Comparison of operational duty pay provisions of Pan American Airways-Flight Engineers Agreement, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    October 25, 1957. Compared with similar provisions of other airline agreements governing non-pilot flight engineers
  - Civil air regulations regarding flight time limitations (Box 1, Folder 56)
    56A. Computation of flight engineers and pilots staffing rate in monthly flight hours per employee. 56B. Hours used for computation of cost impact of Flight Engineers International Association proposals to revise Article II
  - Comparison of flight time limitations provisions of Pan American Airways-Flight Engineers International Association agreement dated October 25, 1957, 1957- 1960 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    Compared with Flight Engineers International Association proposal dated April 15, 1960 and provisions of other airline agreements governing non-pilot flight engineers. Exhibit 56A. Computation of flight engineers and pilots staffing rate in monthly flight
  - Corrected: Analysis of annual cost impact of Flight Engineer International Association proposal to limit flight time to 210 hours per calendar quarter (Box 1, Folder 58)
    Exhibit 57A. Corrected: Analysis of annual cost impact of Flight Engineer International Association proposal to limit flight time to 210 hours per calendar quarter
  - Analysis of the annual cost impact of the Flight Engineers International Association proposal (Box 1, Folder 59)
    Proposal to limit flight engineer duty to 8 hours per flight and total duty to 12 hours in any 24 hour period. Exhibit 58A. Analysis of the annual cost impact of the Flight Engineers International Association proposal to limit flight engineer duty to 8 ho
  - Comparison of "Actual of Scheduled" Provisions of Pan American Airways-Flight Engineer International Association Agreement dated October 25, 1957, 1957- 1960 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    Compared with Flight Engineers International Association Proposal dated April 15, 1960 and similar provisions of other airline agreements governing non pilot flight engineers.
  - Corrected: Analysis of annual cost impact of Flight Engineers International Association proposal to credit scheduled or actual flight time, whichever is greater (Box 1, Folder 61)
    Exhibit 60A.Corrected: Analysis of annual cost impact of Flight Engineers International Association proposal to credit scheduled or actual flight time, whichever is greater
  - Comparison of minimum flight time credit for time away provisions of Pan American Airways-Flight Engineers International Association agreement dated October 25, 1957, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    Compared with Flight Engineers International Association proposal dated April 15, 1960, Pan American Airways-Flight Engineers International Association understanding dated October 2, 1960, and similar provisions of other airline agreements governing non-p
  - Analysis of Annual Impact of Flight Engineers International Association Proposal to provide flight time credits for time away (Article II(d)) (Box 1, Folder 63)
    Exhibit 62A. Analysis of Annual Impact of Flight Engineers International Association Proposal to provide flight time credits for flight time limitation and flying pay purposes
  - Comparison of minimum credit for reporting for flight duty provisions of Pan American Airways-Flight Engineers International Association agreement dated October 25, 1957, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    Compared with Flight Engineers International Association proposal dated April 15, 1960 and similar provisions of other airline agreements governing non-pilot flight engineers
  - Comparison of days free of duty provisions of Pan American Airways-Flight engineers International Association agreement dated October 25, 1957, 1957- 1960 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Analysis of annual cost impact of Flight Engineers International Association proposal, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    Proposal to give engineers 10 or more calendar days free of duty each calendar month and 36 or more calendar days free of duty each calendar quarter at their base station (based on 10 percent sample for third quarter, 1960). Exhibit 65A.Analysis of annual
  - Monthly average days away from base station by status and equipment for first three quarters of 1960 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - History of activities and earnings of selected flight engineer officers (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Examples of elapsed time patterns for piston equipment where single engineer utilized (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Examples of patterns for piston equipment showing high percentage of ground time to total time where single engineer utilized (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - typical piston schedules for 1958 for Latin American Division/New York-based flight engineers (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Typical jet schedules for 1961 for Overseas Division/New York-based B-707 and DC-8 flight engineers (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Typical B-707 schedules as awarded to Trans-World Airlines flight engineers in the International Operation/New York Base for the second quarter in 1961 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Typical B-707 schedules as awarded to American Airlines Los Angeles- and Dallas-based flight engineers for second quarter in 1961 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Flight engineer schedule policy New York Base (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Flight Engineer monthly printed schedule DC-8 Aircraft Overseas Division - IDL Base (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Comparison of base station scheduling policy provisions of Pan American Airways-flight Engineers International Association agreement dated October 25, 1957, 1957- 1960 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Comparison of restriction on dual aircraft assignments provision of Pan American Airways-Flight Engineers International Association agreement dated October 25, 1957, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Comparison of traveling expense and layover facilities provisions of Pan American Airways-Flight Engineers International Association Agreement dated October 25, 1957, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Estimated annual increased cost impact of Flight Engineers International Association proposal (Box 1, Folder 80)
    Proposal to provide single room accommodations with present classification structure
  - Estimated annual increased cost impact of Flight Engineers International Association proposal to provide single room accommodations (Box 1, Folder 81)
    Estimated annual increased cost impact of Flight Engineers International Association proposal to provide single room accommodations for flight engineer officers governing effect to proposal for automatic promotion of Assistant Flight Engineer Officers.
  - Comparison of vacation provisions of Pan American Airways-Flight Engineers International Association Agreement dated October 25, 1957, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Excerpts from Report to the President by the Emergency Board Number 122 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Pan American's return on investment and deficiency below 10.5 percent return (Box 1, Folder 84)
    Excluding capital gains on flight equipment for the years 1957, 1958, 1959, and 1960
  - Cost of jet equipment program and source of funds (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Comparison of operating revenues and expenses and operating ratios by months, 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 86)
    1958, 1959, 1960, and first quarter of 1961
  - Comparison of number of passengers carried by Pan American and by all International Air Transport Association Carriers, 1956-1960 (Box 1, Folder 87)
    Compared with Pan American's percent of total areas for the first six months of 1956, 1957, 1958, 1959, and 1960
  - Comparison of number of scheduled flights operated by Transatlantic International Air Transport Association Carriers, 1956-1960 (Box 1, Folder 88)
    July 1956, 1957, 1958, 1959, and 1960
  - Additional competitive United States-Latin American air services established since July 1, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Competitive weekly flight frequencies in the Pacific Area 1, 1956-1960 (Box 1, Folder 90)
    July 1956, 1957, 1958, 1959, 1960
  - Statistics regarding changes in wage rates (Box 1, Folder 91)
    During the last five years the new income produced per employee has decreased 54.3 percent despite the fact that the average investment required per employee increased 104 percent while net income per employee per $1,000 investment decreased 77.6 percent
  - Operating expenses per employee have increased at a faster rate than operating revenues per employee, resulting in a steadily worsening position, 1956- 1960 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Comparison of the percentage of increase in the weight available for revenue and the operating cost per flight hour (Box 1, Folder 93)
    Comparison for the DC-7C and DC-8 on a NYK-ROM and NYK-PAR Flight
  - Comparison of base station transfer expenses provisions of Pan American Airways-Flight Engineers International Association agreement dated October 25, 1957, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Computation of increased individual transfer costs between selected bases as proposed by Flight Engineers International Association Article 12(j) (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Pertinent provisions of Title II, The Railway Labor Act, as amended (Box 1, Folder 96)